GORDON: Previously on Gotham...
SOFIA: Harvey is weak,
and how many more cops need to
die because of his incompetence?
As of this moment, I'm assuming
the Captaincy of Gotham Central.
Nothing in Gotham is free.
You wanted a gangster to
help you get rid of Penguin.
This is what that
help looks like.
The whole town has gone
hog wild for the Pyg. (SNORTS)
GORDON: Turns out the Pyg's
real name is Lazlo Valentine.
And he just escaped.
LEE: I haven't been looking
for a cure for your brain, Ed,
because I was afraid
that if I told you the truth,
you would go back to
being who you were before.
And I like who you've become.
BRUCE: I'm not the
hero Gotham needs.
- I took the dark path.
- ALFRED: Yes, you did.
And it's gonna be a
long, bumpy journey back.
- What...
- Hello, Victor.
- Where's the boy?
- SOFIA: Alive, for now.
If Oswald wants
to keep it that way,
he will meet me under
the Crown Point Bridge...
You wanted a
war, you've got one!
We will wait for Mr. Cobblepot
to send instructions.
Ahh!
(ALL GRUNTING)
Hello.
Where is Penguin, little man?
This is Gordon. I need
forensics in West End Alley.
A black-market
doc. Pyg was here.
Looks like he got a new face.
(CHOKING)
(MR. PENN SCREAMING)
So, Penguin's out building
support amongst the gangs.
Pretty soon every criminal in
Gotham is gonna be hunting us.
He's out building support
because we made him look weak.
We kill him, and all the
gangs will support me.
- I'm still a Falcone.
- Yeah, you mentioned that.
- About a billion times.
- (DOOR OPENS)
(EXHALES) He doesn't
know where Penguin is.
(CELL PHONE VIBRATES)
(SIGHS) What?
I'll be right there.
Is that about Penguin?
No.
Harper.
We were an hour outside of Gotham
when I got waylaid by Victor Zsasz.
He took Sofia. Gave me
this. I woke up in Virginia.
Damn it. I had a
deal with Penguin.
There's more. We're getting
word Penguin had some
meeting under the Crown
Point Bridge late last night.
Gunfire. A car blown up.
Sofia Falcone was there.
All right, we have to
find Penguin. Harper?
- I'm good, Cap.
- Put out a citywide BOLO.
- I'll find Sofia.
- HARPER: What about the Pyg?
- I heard he escaped from Arkham.
- Tracked him to a black market surgeon.
He's already got a new
face. Lazlo Valentine is gone.
- But if we don't find him...
- Focus on the bigger problem.
We've got a war to stop, people.
So, you're gonna tell us why
we're at your dad's house?
Why do you think?
Sofia.
You look tired.
Ms. Kean, it's good
to see you again.
Likewise. So this is weird.
Why are you here, Father?
What did I tell you when you
asked to return to Gotham?
- I know...
- (LOUDLY) What did I tell you?
- That I wasn't ready.
- Exactly.
And you came back anyway.
Perhaps I should've acted
then. But I was indulgent.
Curious. Who is this
daughter I raised?
Father, Penguin is weak.
If you help me, we can end this.
I don't want Gotham.
I don't believe that.
You love this city.
I used to, yes.
But I'm dying, Sofia.
Someone else can have Gotham.
What I care about now is my family.
And I'm your family. And I want this. I
deserve this. Gotham belongs to me.
Your actions have
disgraced our family.
Tell me how sleeping
with Jim Gordon,
the man who killed your
brother, helped reclaim Gotham.
I'm sorry, what?
I have done many things
I will have to answer for.
But I always knew
the meaning of honor.
You have proven that you do not.
Children... (CHUCKLES)
- They can be such disappointments.
- (SELINA GASPS)
I kill him, and this
is over. Please.
You know why I came
when Penguin called?
It's because you
were going to lose.
If you were anyone
but my daughter,
you'd be dead right now.
Oh. Morning.
In there.
ALFRED: Dear, oh, dear.
Oh. Good morning, Officer.
My name is Alfred Pennyworth.
Neighbors called
in a noise complaint.
- He's all yours.
- Thank you.
Right.
(SCOFFS)
(ALL GASPING)
- Good morning, Master Bruce.
- WOMAN: Oh, my God!
I do believe the party
is well and truly over.
Morning, miss.
Good morning, miss.
GCPD.
- I'm looking...
- For my daughter.
You can stop. She's with me.
GORDON: Carmine.
I didn't expect to see you.
I imagine not. I
arrived this morning.
- You heard Sofia is in danger.
- Was in danger.
I made a deal with Cobblepot.
I take her out of Gotham
today and she lives.
I made the same
deal, he didn't keep it.
He will with me.
I'm glad I never killed you.
Thanks.
Don't thank me. Killing you
would have been a kindness.
You have no idea what
you've brought to your city.
I imagine when you find out
the truth, it will destroy you.
That's a comfort.
Another day. Another man
sending me out of Gotham.
We're both just trying
to keep you alive.
Tell yourself that.
But what I know is that
neither of you believed in me.
Could have been so different.
Goodbye, James Gordon.
I doubt we'll see
each other again.
The sun never shines here.
Everything I did,
I did for your love.
That doesn't matter, does it?
What matters is that after
everything you've done,
I still consider
you my daughter.
That's enough.
Mother planted those
roses, she loved them.
I wanna take one with me.
Get down!
(GASPS)
(INAUDIBLE)
Gotham is still reeling
from the violent death
of Carmine Falcone
three days ago.
Falcone ruled the Gotham
underworld for nearly 30 years.
No arrests have been
made and a strange quiet...
Pleasant night, Master Bruce?
There's a mess in the
Rolls. You'll need a bucket.
MALE NEWSCASTER: which many
have attributed to the Pax Penguina.
Indeed, the Don's claim
to the throne of Gotham...
He shouldn't have come back.
More recent years by a
new breed of criminal...
Leaving some to
ask, does Gotham...
Yes, Victor?
You would've told me, right? If
you were gonna ice the old man.
(SCOFFS) Obviously! Victor,
I did not kill Don Falcone.
Well, everyone on the
street thinks you did.
So let 'em. My hands are
clean. You have my word.
MALE NEWSCASTER:
With Don Falcone's passing,
it is unknown how or indeed
when the void of power
at the center of the city's
underworld will be filled.
(CHOIR SINGING)
GORDON: Sofia.
- I came to the hospital.
- I told them not to admit you.
- I am truly sorry about your father.
- You know it was Penguin.
And if I had evidence
supporting that, I'd arrest him.
He is over there, waiting
to see my face and gloat.
He is a liar. And a
murderer many times over.
But you need evidence.
I have to bury my father.
Excuse us.
(GASPS)
Victor!
- (SIGHS) Harvey.
- Jim.
Your leave is almost up.
- Be good to have you back.
- We'll see.
So why haven't you
arrested the little weasel?
Penguin still owns the judges.
If I arrest him, and it's
not rock solid, he'll walk.
So him whacking Falcone
and you sitting on your hands,
what good does that do?
It was Sofia who paid off the
Mayor to make me Captain.
I didn't ask her to.
Well, well.
She's been pressing me to
move on Penguin. Even before this.
I told you, didn't I?
That bill would come due.
I can't allow her to turn the
GCPD into her own private army.
We've come too far.
This has to be by the book.
Then forget Falcone.
Penguin's too smart to
get nailed for that anyway.
What do you mean?
Get him to do something
you can really bust him for.
And then yank his ass off
the street once and for all.
- You're saying start a war.
- I'm saying get him to start one.
You know he's
gonna come for her.
I don't give a tinker's
damn about Sofia.
Way I see it, everything
that's happened,
down to Don Falcone
lying in that box,
comes from you deciding
months ago to go after Penguin.
This is all on you.
So finish what you started.
PENGUIN: Goodbye, old friend.
I will not forget all
that you taught me.
I had great respect
for your father.
But once he's in
the ground, you are...
- Excuse me.
- (BREATHES HEAVILY)
Not here.
What're you doing, Jim?
Finishing what I started.
(INDISTINCT CHATTERING)
Testing, testing, one,
two, three. James Gordon.
James Gordon.
GORDON: What do
you want, Oswald?
You know what I
want. Where is she?
No.
You're seriously going
to go to war for her?
I'm upholding the law.
No one gets to decide
who lives or dies in Gotham.
Can you not see, Jim? She's
manipulated you and lied...
The law is the law.
Now either get over it or
face the consequences.
(MICROPHONE FEEDBACK)
Let's try it this way.
Sofia Falcone is in this
building, whoever brings her to me
will be richly rewarded.
I'm going to count to five.
Count as much
as you want, twerp.
Yeah, we don't work for you.
This man is asking you to risk
your lives to protect a gangster!
I am offering you money. Huh?
And bonus, no one
gets killed. (LAUGHS)
Hey, Captain, can we?
Sure.
Get off me.
Blood will run, Jim. Mark
my words! Blood will run!
It will be on your hands!
(PENGUIN YELLING)
(OFFICERS JEERING)
From the first day
I put on the badge,
I was told things
could never change.
Gotham was corrupt.
GCPD was corrupt.
Criminals and
lowlifes ran things.
You just showed me different.
Penguin will be coming.
It's time we showed
Gotham who we are.
Suit up.
(GUNS COCKING)
(INDISTINCT SHOUTING)
Just let us go. You've
obviously got your hands full.
- Shut up!
- Whatever.
They'll all be dead
in a few minutes.
Listen, you stupid... (GROANS)
(INDISTINCT CHATTER
ON LOUDSPEAKER)
(GUNFIRE CONTINUES)
More left.
She means your left.
Then say that.
Your left! Your left! Your left!
- Hmm.
- (SIGHS)
Yay. Teamwork!
(INDISTINCT CHATTERING)
- SOFIA: You're winning.
- So far.
But every gang in Gotham
owes Penguin allegiance.
I can't arrest them all.
So arrest Penguin,
wasn't that the point?
As long as he's using
proxies, he's protected.
I have to keep pressing him.
When his back
is against the wall,
he'll do something he
can't take back or explain.
And then I'll have him.
So, you're baiting him into
committing a public atrocity.
What if he already has?
There's this boy from my orphanage.
Martin. Oswald cared for him.
I hid him away for his safety.
But Oswald forced me into
telling him where Martin was,
and then put him in
a car, and blew it up.
Why didn't you
tell me this before?
Because I'm his enemy.
Who's going to believe me?
Also, I didn't see
him plant the bomb.
- So you have nothing?
- I didn't say that.
Oswald never understood the
way people cared for my father.
And one of those
people just called me.
How is Jim Gordon beating us?
Well, every cop in
Gotham is behind him.
I'm guessing he has
great leadership skills.
Victor, when this
is said and done,
you and I need to have a frank
discussion about chain of command.
But now, go do something
horrific! Show the GCPD exactly...
GORDON: Oswald Cobblepot,
you're under arrest.
Have you completely
lost your mind?
Nobody has to die. We
only want Cobblepot!
Well, see, Jim, that's a
problem, as they work for me.
But just so I know,
what's the charge?
Murder.
Enough! Enough! I
did not kill Don Falcone!
And I dare you to
prove otherwise.
GORDON: It's not for Falcone.
I'm arresting you for the murder
of the boy you blew up
under the Crown Point Bridge.
(SNICKERING)
What's so funny?
Nothing. Well, everything,
actually, 'cause you see,
he's not dead. (LAUGHS)
I only faked his death
so that Sofia Falcone
couldn't use him against me.
She's the one who told
you I killed him, isn't she?
Then where is he?
(STAMMERS) I don't know. Victor
took him out of Gotham, tell him.
ZSASZ: What's to tell?
You blew that kid sky-high.
PENGUIN: What?
You sent that pipsqueak
to kingdom come.
No! That's not true!
And I'll testify to that.
What?
Look, I ain't taking the
rap for no kid murder.
- (YELLS)
- GORDON: Get him out of here!
You are lying! You
are a lying traitor!
Victor Zsasz is a
liar! No! I will kill you!
Traitor!
GORDON: This doesn't give
you a free pass, you know.
Jim...
Not now.
You did it, Cap. You won.
(CHEERING)
So I'm guessing Gordon doesn't
know the kid's actually alive.
Jim Gordon played his part.
He showed the underworld
that Penguin was weak.
That he did. End of the day...
He's a Cobblepot.
You are a Falcone.
Smile, ladies. It's a new day.
So, Sofia was as good as
her word, we got our club back.
Yippee. We get to
serve drinks again.
It's just a base of operations.
But I am meeting with the designer
later to make it less Penguiny.
Have fun.
Music to soothe
the savage beast?
Something like that.
Alfred?
Oh, the front page is up?
Didn't expect you
to brave the light
of the day for couple
more hours, Master B.
Tommy wanted to go to the
horse races. What's all this?
It's a little project of mine.
I like to call it, Operation
Save Bruce Wayne.
(SCOFFS)
Switzerland.
Few months up in the
Alps, you'll be tickety-boo.
Are you going to kidnap me?
No, I'm going to appeal
to your better angels.
And if that doesn't
work, I shall beg.
Please, Master Bruce.
If for no other
reason, do it for me.
These past weeks, you know how
much I've thought about Ra's al Ghul?
About my parents?
Not at all, Alfred.
- All you're offering me is pain.
- Well, there is no life without pain.
There's no love,
there is no joy.
I don't know about that. I
am having a fair amount of joy.
You're bloody miserable is
what you are, mate. I can see it.
Alfred, I know
you care about me.
But I am asking you to
stop what you are doing.
I'm not who you thought I was.
I'm not who my parents
might've wanted me to be.
- And I'm okay with that.
- But I'm not okay with it.
- And I don't believe it.
- And that's your problem.
Now, I'm gonna go meet Tommy.
Can't let you do
that, Master Bruce.
(SIGHS)
You gonna stop me?
- If need be, yes.
- (SCOFFS)
You really think you can?
Oh, I know I can.
I just don't want
you to make me try.
Well...
(BOTH GRUNTING)
(OBJECTS CLATTERING)
Don't do this, Master Bruce.
No, Alfred, we're doing this.
(BOTH GRUNTING)
Getting slayed, Master Bruce.
Haven't been training, have you, son?
- Got a bit of ring rust.
- Really?
Because you're the only
one breathing hard, old man.
(GROANS)
- Stop it, will ya? Stop it! Stop!
- Fine! Fine.
Oh, no. Master Bruce, I'm so sorry.
I don't know what came over me...
(DOOR CLOSES)
I am in control.
(LAUGHS)
I am in control. Me. Ed Nygma.
But why would you want that?
You don't understand.
We had so much
fun when we were me.
Oh, no.
Tell me it's not that.
Not what?
I leave when
spurned. I give all.
I take nothing. I can raise you to
a king, or make you to a beggar.
What am I?
I'm just gonna tell you 'cause
you're not going to get it.
- Love.
- I am in control!
You're in love with Lee
Thompkins, you pathetic loser.
Shut up!
Ed angry at mirror?
No, Grundy. I am
not angry at the mirror.
- Ed angry at Ed?
- That is...
Surprisingly perceptive.
(SIGHS) I need some air.
(DOOR CLOSES)
(MUSIC PLAYING ON GRAMOPHONE)
This was the end
of Solomon Grundy
Huh?
(GROANS)
This was the end
of Solomon Grundy
(GRUNTING)
- Where is Grundy?
- I kidnapped you.
For the record,
you're not light.
What pretty lady want?
When we were fighting, you
called me "Tabby," remember?
- Grundy want to go back to friend Ed.
- Ed...
Right, your friend.
Well, your best friend Ed
tied you and me to chairs,
electrocuted you,
and cut off my hand.
Look at the scar. Ring a bell?
(EXHALES)
Remember me, Butch. I'm Tabby.
I'm your Tabby.
Grundy sorry.
Yeah. I'm sorry too.
Before, when you said my
name, I'd just hit you in the head.
Maybe that's the only way.
So you're gonna
remember me, Butch...
Or I'm gonna beat your head in.
- Pretty lady...
- (GRUNTS)
When I called, I wasn't
sure you would come.
I was going to anyway.
We need to talk.
I agree.
I'm going to ask you not to
do what you're about to do.
Which is?
Unify the gangs.
Put the Falcones back in
charge of the underworld.
But wasn't that our deal?
I'd replace Penguin. You'd
be the law, I'd be the order?
No. And if you try and take
over, I'll have to come after you.
James. You're nothing
if not predictable.
(CLICKS TONGUE) Now, I think
it's time you heard my proposal.
- I'm not interested.
- I think you are.
MAN: Surprise.
(GUN COCKS)
I know, you thought I'd have
a different face because
I killed that doctor.
But that was just to
throw you off the scent.
That's not why he's
surprised, Lazlo.
THE PYG: Can I tell him?
You came to this beautiful
woman because you had a problem.
A Penguin problem. Pax
Penguina was gonna last.
But Sofia had an idea.
I'd heard of a contract killer that
was impersonating serial killers, so.
What if there was a killer,
a real vicious son of a bitch,
hunting the police,
all slice and dice.
SOFIA: I needed the
police to turn on Penguin.
I knew a few cops
would have to die.
So you sent this
monster to my city?
I let him improvise.
I'll admit, got a
little carried away
with the whole (CHUCKLES)
"cooking folks" routine.
I really got in the role.
You know, only hiccup was
that mess with her daddy.
That was you.
I gave him a chance, Jim.
And if he would've shown
one iota of appreciation
for everything I have
done for this family,
for him... He would be alive.
GORDON: But I saw you shot.
There was another shooter there.
SOFIA: I had to do something
to throw off suspicion.
THE PYG: Well, she
wasn't about to get herself
plugged by a bunch
of yahoos in a car.
It was some pretty
shooting, if I do say so.
I missed all her vital parts.
I'm putting you in jail.
And this time it's Blackgate.
- You are gonna rot in there.
- Jim...
(GUNSHOT)
(INHALES DEEPLY)
That's done now.
(CLATTERS)
My father had his moment
of truth. This is yours.
How many cops died under
the Pax Penguina? Not one.
It was you who
couldn't stomach it.
It was you who came
to the Falcones for help.
There is a direct line
from your decision
to a dozen police officers who
have been brutally murdered.
You are insane.
Why not just kill me?
Because, Jim...
I need you at the
head of the GCPD.
- I need...
- Someone you can control.
You've been planning this
since the day we first met.
This isn't about
Gotham. This is revenge.
For me killing Mario.
(GUN THUDS)
You want to arrest
me, arrest me.
But I will talk.
And the cops that died,
the friend that you betrayed,
will all have been for nothing.
The GCPD will crumble.
Penguin, or someone worse,
will take over and you
will lose Gotham forever.
Or, take on the sin as your own.
Keep the GCPD. Let
them think you're a hero.
But live knowing who
you are. What you've done.
That's my revenge.
(PHONE BEEPS)
FEMALE OFFICER: GCPD.
GCPD, how can I help you?
Hello? Anyone there? Anybody?
This is Gordon.
I'm at Sofia Falcone's...
I just shot and killed the Pyg.
Oh, thank Christ. You're safe.
Master Bruce, listen, I
don't want to fight anymore.
You win.
If this is how you want to deal
with what you've been
going through, then so be it.
I'm not gonna try and stop you.
But just know this...
You will remember who you are,
and when you do,
I will be right here...
No, you won't be.
I went to my lawyer and had
him draw up emancipation papers.
You're no longer
my legal guardian.
I won't sign them.
You don't have to.
Now I'm going out.
If you're still here
when I get back,
I'll go to the police
and show them my face.
- Master Bruce, please...
- Alfred, you're fired.
Now get the hell
out of my house.
(DOOR CLOSES)
(PANTING)
Butch! Say something!
Say something.
(PIPE CLATTERS)
(GROANS)
I'm sorry.
I tried.
(LAUGHING)
(INDISTINCT CHATTERING)
Harvey.
I was just, uh,
dropping something off.
Oh, I heard you got the Pyg.
- And Penguin.
- Yeah.
So everything turned out well.
- You didn't even need me...
- You got a second? Could we, uh...
They, uh, believe in
you. Don't let them down.
What the hell happened to me?
PENGUIN: Traitors.
Every single one of them.
I'll kill her! I will
flay her alive!
Her and Gordon and Zsasz and...
(BANGING)
- MAN: Hey, buddy...
- (GASPS)
- Do not talk to me.
- I get it, pal...
This place is full of loonies.
I just thought, we could
help each other out.
And how can you
help me? (CHUCKLES)
Well, not to toot my own horn,
but I'm a very resourceful fellow.
So, toot. Toot, toot!
(MAN CACKLES)
(GASPS)
I know that laugh.
What do you say, pal?
I'll be your best friend.
(GASPS)
Give me a smile...
(LAUGHS)
English - SDH